Guide to the Phyllis Chesler Papers, 1968-2003 RL.00221
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Phyllis Chesler papers
1968-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Chesler, Phyllis
RL.00221
118 Linear Feet
The papers of Phyllis Chesler are divided into the following series: Writings, Custody Speakout Project, Women and Health Organizations, and Personal and Professional Papers. Chesler's Writings are separated into subseries by titles of her published works, and comprise the bulk of the collection. These papers include research files, interviews, and chapter drafts for her books Women and Madness; Women, Money and Power; About Men; Mothers on Trial; and Sacred Bond. The detailed research files in the Writings Series also contain audio tapes and selected transcripts of interviews conducted by Chesler in conjunction with her research on women and mental health, women's history, child custody (particularly the "Baby M" case involving the lawsuit between Mary Beth Whitehead and William Stern and baby Melissa Stern), and feminist concerns. The Writings Series includes Chesler's miscellaneous writings and provides insight into her personal and professional life through correspondence, manuscripts and notes surrounding each work as well as clippings and records documenting her feminist activism. Among the major correspondents are Carolyn Shaw Bell, Sheila Kaplan, Kate Millet, Tillie Olsen, Grace Paley, Adrienne Rich, Donna Shalala, Susan Sontag, and Gloria Steinem.
88,500 Items
Access Restrictions
The Phyllis Chesler Papers contain sensitive information regarding persons other than Phyllis Chesler. Therefore, patrons who wish to use this collection must sign a research agreement, which may be obtained from any Special Collections reference staff person.
The collection also includes oral history interviews in the form of audio recordings and hardcopy transcripts that do not have release forms transferring intellectual property rights from interviewees or interviewers to researchers using this collection. Researchers are cautioned that the publication of information contained in these interviews may violate the legal rights of interviewees or interviewers. It is the sole responsibility of researchers to secure permission from interviewees or interviewers to publish quotes from either, and to ensure that information gained from research in this collection is not used in any way that violates rights remaining with interviewees, interviewers or their heirs.
Access Restrictions
Access note. Collection contains electronic records that may need to be reformatted. Access copies of electronic records require special equipment. Contact Research Services for access.
Provenance
The Phyllis Chesler Papers were purchased, 1992-1994. Additional materials received in 2000, 2003, and 2004.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into the following series: Writings, Custody Speakout Project, Women and Health Organizations, Personal and Professional Papers, International Committee for Women of the Wall, On the Issues, and Chronic Fatigue Syndrome.
Biographical Note
1940, Oct. 1 Born in Brooklyn, NY to Leon and Lillian (Hammer) Chesler
1962 Bard College, B.A.
1967 New School for Social Research, M.A.
1968-1969 Clinical research associate at Metropolitan Hospital, New York City Psychotherapy intern at Washington Square Institute for Psychotherapy and Mental Health Graduate study at New York Medical College
1969 New School for Social Research, Ph.D.
1969-1998 Professor of psychology at the College of Staten Island of the City University of New York
1970 Cofounder, Association for Women in Psychology Psychotherapist in private practice Lecturer at various institutions, including Instititute for Developmental Studies and New School for Social Research
1972 Charter member of board of directors of Women's Action Alliance
1974 Member of board of directors of Center for the Study of Psychiatry
1976 Cofounder of National Women's Health Network
1997- Research associate at International Research Institute on Jewish Women, Brandeis University
1998 Professor Emerita of City University of New York
Collection Overview
The papers of psychologist, radical feminist author, and professor Phyllis Chesler span the dates 1968-2001. For the most part, Chesler's original folder titles have been maintained throughout the collection. The collection is divided into the following series: Writings, Custody Speakout Project, Women and Health Organizations, Personal and Professional Papers, International Committee for Women of the Wall, On the Issues, and Chronic Fatigue Syndrome. Chesler's Writings are separated into subseries by titles of her published works, and comprise the bulk of the collection. These papers include research files, interviews, and chapter drafts for her books Women and Madness; Women, Money and Power; About Men; With Child; Mothers on Trial; Sacred Bond; and Letters to a Young Feminist. The detailed research files in the Writings Series also contain audiocassettes and selected transcripts of interviews conducted by Chesler in conjunction with her research on women and mental health, women's history, childbirth and pregnancy, child custody and surrogate mothers (particularly the "Baby M" controversy concerning Mary Beth Whitehead and the Stern family), and feminist concerns. The Writings Series includes Chesler's miscellaneous writings and provides insight into her personal and professional life through correspondence, manuscripts, and notes surrounding each work as well as clippings and records documenting her feminist activism. Materials related to Women of the Wall: Claiming Sacred Ground can be found in the International Committee for Women of the Wall Series. Chesler's complete writings from 1991 to the present, as well as selected archives of her writings from the 1970s and 1980s are available at her website, The Phyllis Chesler Organization.
The Personal and Professional Papers Series is subdivided into the following subseries:Teaching Material, which provides insight into Chesler's feminist activism and includes student evaluations and selected student papers for classes at the College of Staten Island and CUNY; Publicity Files, which contain reviews of Chesler's work as well as articles by and about her; Juvenilia, which documents Chesler's artistic and intellectual development through high school; People Files, Financial Papers, Correspondence, and Invitations. These latter four subseries document aspects of Chesler's personal and professional relationships and her family life. Among the major correspondents in the People Files Subseries are Carolyn Shaw Bell, Sheila Kaplan, Kate Millett, Tillie Olsen, Grace Paley, Adrienne Rich, Donna Shalala, Susan Sontag, and Gloria Steinem. The Custody Speakout Project Series and the Women and Health Organizations Series document Chesler's concern and activism for women's health and custody rights, while the International Committee for Women of the Wall Series documents Chesler's involvement in activism surrounding the right of women to pray at the Kotel with a Torah scroll, as well as her work as co-editor of the anthology Women of the Wall: Claiming Sacred Ground. The On The Issues Series contains correspondence, article and column drafts, pre-published and published issue files, financial materials, meeting notes, and other papers related to the publication of On The Issues, a quarterly feminist magazine. Chesler served as an editor-at-large for the magazine, and she correspondedfrequently and worked closely with its publisher and editor-in-chief, Merle Hoffman. The Chronic Fatigue Syndrome Series contains Chesler's research and drafts of writings on Chronic Fatigue Syndrome, also referred to by the acronyms CFS and CFIDS.
Many American feminists are represented in Chesler's personal and professional correspondence in the Writings Series as well as the People Files Subseries of the Personal and Professional Papers Series. The Invitations Subseries in that series documents Chesler's involvement in feminist, environmental, and other political events and protests. The Teaching Materials Subseries and the People Files Subseries contain correspondence, clippings, notes, and other miscellaneous materials related to individuals and institutions with which Chesler was in contact in the 1970s and 1980s. Much of the material in the People Files Subseries documents Chesler's personal and professional concerns following the publication of Women, Money and Power and prior to publication of About Men and With Child, with a particular emphasis on her relationships with other feminist writers and activists.
Chesler's professional literary career is documented in the Correspondence Subseries of the Personal and Professional Papers Series which focuses on Chesler's relationships with publishers, promotion for her books, and royalty statements related to Chesler's books. The Financial Papers Subseries also documents Chesler's business concerns and professional expenses. Further correspondence with publishers can be found in the research files of individual subseries within the Writings Series. The Women and Health Organizations Series, Custody Speakout Project Series, and the Invitations Subseries subseries of the Personal and Professional Papers Series provide information regarding the organizations supported by Chesler.
Chesler's attention to women's custody rights appears in the Writings Series within the Mothers on Trial Subseries. The bulk of Chesler's work on child custody is documented in the Custody Speakout Project Series which contains organizational files including proposals, resource lists, fundraising projects, speaker information and agenda files for the Custody Speakout Project.
Sex role; Pregnancy -- Psychological aspects; Mothers -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Mother and child; Power (Social sciences); Mothers -- United States -- Biography; Feminism -- Religious aspects -- Judaism; Feminists -- United States -- Biography; Mental illness; Men -- Psychology; Surrogate mothers -- United States -- Case studies; Surrogate mothers -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States -- Case studies; Custody of children -- United States -- Case studies; Childbirth -- Psychological aspects; Women -- Health and hygiene -- Sociological aspects; Wealth -- United States; Women -- United States -- Social conditions; Women -- Psychologists; Women's rights -- United States; Chronic fatigue syndrome; Sontag, Susan, 1933-; Steinem, Gloria; Rich, Adrienne Cecile; Shalala, Donna E.; Olsen, Tillie; Paley, Grac; Kaplan, Sheila, 1945-; Millett, Kate; Whitehead, Mary Beth -- Trials, litigation, etc.; Women of the Wall (Organization: Israel); Stern, Melissa, 1986-; Stern, William, 1946 -- -Trials, litigation, etc.; Bell, Carolyn Shaw; Chesler, Phyllis; Chesler, Phyllis -- Women, Money and Power; Chesler, Phyllis -- Women and Madness; Chesler, Phyllis -- With Child: A Diary of Motherhood; Chesler, Phyllis -- Sacred Bond: The Legacy of Baby M; Chesler, Phyllis -- Mothers on Trial: The Battle for Children and Custody; Chesler, Phyllis -- About Men; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Writings Series, 1969-1988 and undated
  Scope and Contents note
  The Writings Series is divided into subseries by the titles of Chesler's published works: Women and Madness; Women Money and Power; About Men; With Child; Mothers on Trial; Sacred Bond; and Letters to a Young Feminist. There is also a short subseries of Miscellaneous Writings.
  - Women and Madness Subseries, 1969-1980 (bulk 1969-1971)
    The Women and Madness Subseries, 1969-1980, (bulk 1969-1971) is composed of Research files, Correspondence, Chapter Drafts, and Audiocassettes.
    - Research Files
      These files are primarily subject files, interview transcripts, statistical reports, and clippings. The folders maintain Chesler's original titles and are arranged alphabetically.
      - Adolescence (Box W1)
      - Agnes C. (Box W1)
      - Amazons (3 folders) (Box W1)
      - Angry and paranoid women (Box W1)
      - Asher Suicide (Box W1)
      - Bad Experiences with Male/Female Therapists (Box W1)
      - Biological - Genetic Superiority (Box W1)
      - Bardwick - "Current Myths" (Box W1)
      - B., Helen (Box W1)
      - Category and Coding Checklist (Box W1)
      - Clinical Examples - confidential illustration (Box W1)
      - Clippings - miscellaneous (Box W1)
      - Cooper: Death in the family (Box W1)
      - Dahomey - Burton (Box W1)
      - Dictation - Miscellaneous. (Box W1)
      - Doris (Box W1)
      - Eleanor Packard (Box W1)
      - Female Sexuality (Box W1)
      - Feminist Questionnaires (Box W1)
      - Feminists - Phyllis, Lila, Dorothy, Pamela, Alicia, Mindy (Box W1)
      - Feminists - Dorothy, Mindy, Alice, Phyllis (Box W1)
      - Feminists - Lila K. (Box W1)
      - Feminists - Lynn, Lila (Box W1)
      - Feminist Notes (Box W1)
      - Grants (Box W1)
      - Helen "X" - Age 70 (Box W1)
      - Laing critique - First Draft (Box W1)
      - Lesbians - Rose Interview (Box W1)
      - Lesbians - Tina, Nancy, Roseann, Ellen, Iris (Box W1)
      - Lesbians - summaries and questionnaires (Box W1)
      - Linda N. (Box W1)
      - Lundberg and Sandheim Modern Women: The Last Sex (Box W1)
      - Madness Network News (Box W1)
      - Maimonides Medical Center (Box W1)
      - Marriage and family (2 folders) (Box W2)
      - Mental Asylum - Summaries and Questionnaires (Box W2)
      - Mental Asylum - Alma, Denise, Debby, Carrie, Aileen, Beatrice (Box W2)
      - Mental Asylum - Helen, Judith, Kathy, Marie (Box W2)
      - Mental Asylum - Justine (Box W2)
      - Miscellaneous Notes (Box W2)
      - "Mistress List" - Master list names of people participating in study (Box W2)
      - Myrna (Box W2)
      - Paranoia (Box W2)
      - The Patient (Box W2)
      - People to contact (Box W2)
      - Private patients in therapy (Box W2)
      - Problems of Women (special therapy) (Box W2)
      - Psychiatric Careers of women (Box W2)
      - Psychoanalytic Therapy (Box W2)
      - "Psychology Today" (Box W2)
      - "Psychotherapy and Women" (Box W2)
      - Quotes (Box W2)
      - S. Angrist Book (Box W2)
      - Schizophrenia (Box W2)
      - Sex Diagnosis categories (Box W2)
      - Sex role alienation - mental health (Box W2)
      - Sex typed Diagnostic Categories (Box W2)
      - Sex-Type Diagnosis (Box W2)
      - Sex with Therapists (2 folders) (Box W2)
      - Sex with Therapists - Cassandra (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Chip (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Helen (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Laura (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Lydia (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Margaret (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Muriel (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Pat (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Renee (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Rochelle (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Sonia (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapist "Summaries and Questionnaires' (Box W3)
      - Sex with Therapists - Sylvia (Box W3)
      - Shelton Tape Notes (Box W3)
      - Social Class (2 folders) (Box W3)
      - Social Class - Socially Prominent Mental Illness (Box W3)
      - Statistics (5 folders) (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Age Adjusted Totals (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Census data, 1970 (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Duplicates - 1961-1968 (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Interview data (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Notes/Mental health (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Overall and 1960-1969 (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Reports: Mental Health (3 folders) (Box W3)
      - Statistics - Reports: Mental Health (4 folders) (Box W4)
      - Statistics - Miscellaneous (Box W4)
      - Statistics - Sex Typed diagnosis (Box W4)
      - Statistics - Table 1 - Diagnostic categories (Box W4)
      - Statistics - Vital Health Statistics (Box W4)
      - Statistics - Z test (Box W4)
      - SUNY - courses (Box W4)
      - Sylvia Plath (Box W4)
      - Szasz - Witchcraft (Box W4)
      - Therapy - evaluated (Box W4)
      - Third World Women - notes (Box W4)
      - Third World Women - quotes (Box W4)
      - Third World Women - Summaries and questionnaires (Box W4)
      - Third World Women - Tamar, Karen, Bernice, Denis, Cortez (Box W4)
      - Wilhelm Reich (Box W4)
      - Women's Movement Press (Box W4)
      - Zelda Fitzgerald (Box W4)
    - Correspondence
      The bulk of the correspondence was received by Chesler after publication of Women and Madness, primarily from individuals relating their own experiences in therapy, requesting information or assistance, or offering their opinion of her work. The subseries maintains Chesler's original subject designations and is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
      - Abuse by Female Therapists (Box W4)
      - Abuse by male psychiatrists (Box W4)
      - Abuse in Mental Asylums (Box W4)
      - Help File: Careers, Education, Information (3 folders) (Box W4)
      - Help File: Desire for Counseling/Therapy (Box W4)
      - Help File: Former Mental Patients (Box W5)
      - Help File: Legal, Medical, Economic, Childcare aid (2 folders) (Box W5)
      - Help File: Desire to Enter Women's Liberation (Box W5)
      - Help File: Miscellaneous Help (Box W5)
      - Housewives Complaints - No psychiatric history (Box W5)
      - Housewives Complaints - Psychiatric history (Box W5)
      - Housewife Horror Stories - Psychiatric Treatment (Box W5)
      - Housewife Horror Stories - No Psychiatric Treatment (Box W5)
      - Help files - volunteers (Box W5)
      - From "The Divine" (2 folders) (Box W5)
      - From Men: Favorable Reactions (Box W5)
      - From Men: Hostile Reactions (Box W5)
      - From Men: Pro and Con (2 folders) (Box W5)
      - From Men: Professionals Pro (Box W5)
      - From Men: Theories with a "twist" (Box W5)
      - From Women - Hostile (Box W5)
      - From Women - Pro: book or article (Box W5)
      - From Women - Pro Phyllis Chesler: TV or lecture (Box W5)
      - From Women - "Pro WL Views with Depressing Tales to Tell." (Box W5)
      - From Women - "Pro WL Views with Good Tales to Tell" (Box W5)
      - From Women: Professionals Pro (Box W5)
      - From Women: Theories on Life, Society, Marriage, etc. (Box W5)
      - Legal Abuse and Medical Abuse (Box W5)
      - Louise Belew Newsletter (2 folders) (Box W5)
      - Media Letters (Box W5)
      - Men in Prison and Mental Asylums (Box W5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box W5)
      - Movement People (Box W5)
      - Professional Groups: Pro (Box W5)
      - Professionals: Con (Box W5)
      - Unsolicited Men and Women 1979-1980 (Box W5)
      - Women in Mental Asylums (Box W5)
    - Chapter Drafts (Box W6)
      The typescripts, handwritten manuscripts, and notes in this subseries are arranged in chapter order with complete manuscripts filed at the end of the subseries. The folder titles reflect those established by Chesler except in cases where the folder title did not reflect the contents of the folder. In these cases each folder's contents were compared to the published version of the text in order to establish titles.
      - Introduction (2 folders) (Box W6)
      - Overall Thesis (Box W6)
      - Acknowledgments (Box W6)
      - Table of Contents (Box W6)
      - Chapter One (7 folders) (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - "Women and Daughters" (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - New (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - notes and quotes (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - Notes and Miscellaneous (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - Footnotes/backup material (Box W6)
      - Chapter One - miscellaneous. (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two (3 folders) (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two, Asylums - Original and carbons (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two - Women in Asylums (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two - Women in Asylums (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two - quotes (Box W6)
      - Chapter Two - footnotes (Box W6)
      - Chapter Three - "The Clinicians" handwritten original and carbon Chapter Three (2 folders) (Box W6)
      - Chapter Three - Clinicians (2 folders) (Box W6)
      - Chapter Three - footnotes "Clinicians" (Box W6)
      - Chapter Three - miscellaneous (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four (2 folders) (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - handwritten original and carbon copy (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - graphs and tables (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - handwritten original and carbon copy (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - Statistics (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - Statistics: The Female Psychiatric Career (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - Female Psychiatric Career (Box W6)
      - Chapter Four - New captions (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - carbon and handwritten original (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - "Sex with Therapist" - original (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - quotations (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - miscellaneous pages (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - backup materials (Box W6)
      - Chapter Five - New "The Interviews" (Box W6)
      - Chapter Six - Women in mental asylums (Box W6)
      - Chapter Seven - Lesbians - original (Box W6)
      - Chapter Seven - Lesbians in therapy (Box W6)
      - Chapter Seven - Lesbianism, quotes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Eight - Third World Women - Original handwritten (Box W7)
      - Chapter Eight - Quotes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Eight - Third World Women (Box W7)
      - Chapter Eight - Third World Women -Transcripts and quotes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Eight - Third World Women Quotes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Nine (Box W7)
      - Chapter Nine - Feminists original handwritten and carbon copy (Box W7)
      - Chapter Nine - Feminists (3 folders) (Box W7)
      - Chapter Nine - carbons (Box W7)
      - Chapter Nine- Quotes (2 folders) (Box W7)
      - New Chapter Ten (Box W7)
      - New Chapter Ten - Quotes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Ten - reworked (Box W7)
      - Chapter Ten - notes (Box W7)
      - Chapter Ten-Eleven - Miscellaneous (Box W7)
      - Chapter Ten (2 folders) (Box W7)
      - "Last Chapter" (Box W7)
      - Appendix A (2 folders) (Box W7)
      - Tables (Box W7)
      - Bibliography (Box W7)
      - Complete Manuscript. Chap 1-5 (Box W7)
      - Complete Manuscript. Chap 6-10 (Box W7)
      - Manuscript, Xerox Copy - Chapters One, Two (Box W7)
      - Manuscript, Xerox Copy - Chapters Three-Five, Ten (Box W7)
      - Manuscript - incomplete (Box W7)
      - Copy edited Manuscript - pg. 1-100 (Box W7)
      - Copy edited Manuscript - pg. 101-200 (Box W7)
      - Copy edited Manuscript - pg. 201-300 (Box W7)
      - Copy edited Manuscript - pg. 301-359 (Box W8)
      - Index (Box W8)
      - Foundry Proof (2 folders) (Box W8)
      - Proofs - miscellaneous pages (Box W8)
      - Galleys (Box W8)
      - Illustrations (Box W8)
      - Art and Illustrations (Box W8)
      - Amazon Art (Box W8)
    - Audiocassettes
      Audiocassettes of interviews conducted while researching Women and Madness, arranged alphabetically according to titles established by Chesler. Several tapes contain more than one interview.
      Conditions Governing Access note
      [Original audiovisual materials are closed to use. Use of these materials requires production of listening or viewing copies. Please contact Research Services before coming to use this collection.]
      - Aileen (Box W8)
      - Agnes (Box W8)
      - Alice K. - Feminist (Box W8)
      - Alma (Box W8)
      - Alma, I (Box W8)
      - Alma C., I-II (Box W8)
      - Bernice - Black Prostitute (Box W8)
      - Betty, I - Lesbian (Box W8)
      - Bici (Box W8)
      - "Black Teacher" (Box W8)
      - Burk (2 audiocassettes) (Box W8)
      - Candy C. (Box W8)
      - Carol G. (Box W8)
      - Carrie (Box W8)
      - Cass - Sex with Therapist (Box W8)
      - Cass, II - Sonia II - Sex with Therapist (Box W8)
      - Cathy L. (Asylum) - Dr. L. (Box W8)
      - Debbie (Box W8)
      - Debbie S. (Box W8)